Finding Aid for School of Kinesiology (University of Michigan) records, 1966-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
School of Kinesiology (University of Michigan) records 1966-2010 1985-1996
University of Michigan. School of Kinesiology.
9987 Bimu 2
Established in 1921 as the Department of Physical Education, the department maintained separate programs for men and women until 1970. In 1984 Physical Education became an independent unit. In 1990 the name was officially changed to School of Kinesiology. In 2008 the Division of Kinesiology was renamed the School of Kinesiology. Records reflect the evolution of kinesiology from a department to independent division. Material includes committee records, curriculum material and topical files.
3.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records were received in 1999 (donor no. 8840.) Website captures in 2002 and 2010
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open without restriction.
With the completion of the Waterman Gym and the appointment of Dr. James Fitzgerald as its director, the University of Michigan began developing a program of physical education for men in 1894. At that time 2,000 men and 500 women were enrolled at the university. Petitioned by the women and supported by President James B. Angell, who stated that women "need the privileges of a gymnasium quite as much as the men," Dr. Eliza M. Mosher, a former Michigan medical student, was appointed to oversee the growing population of women. At this time work began on a women's gymnasium. At the turn of the century, the Barbour Gymnasium was completed.
Around this same era, in 1898, physical education training became formalized, courses were designed, and the Regents passed a resolution making course work in physical education a requirement towards graduation. In the early 1900s physical education programs increased in popularity. In response, the intramural sports program was formally established in 1912. This led to a fairer allocation of equipment and facilities between males and females.
In 1921 the Regents created a Department of Physical Education and established the Division of Hygiene and Public Health, which would include oversight of men's and women's physical education. Dr. John Sundwall was named the first director of the new division. Sundwall rapidly developed the new curriculum for the training of teachers in physical education. The new division was placed within the School of Education, itself a newly established independent academic unit. Prior to July, 1921, Education had been a department in the College of Literature, Science and the Arts.
Both at the University of Michigan and throughout the nation physical education continued to grow and develop as did professional sports. In fact from 1931 to 1938 a graduate program was introduced in a series of three sequences: administration, supervision, and teaching, respectively. In 1949, a new type of physical education research based on the scientific method was introduced by Dr. Paul Hunsicker, professor and chair of the department, whose specialty was movement science. This shift changed kinesiology's theoretical foundations as it marked its movement outside of the boundaries of sports, recreation, and fitness to a wider, more general study of movement.
During the 1970s, a series of changes occurred within the Department of Physical Education. Beginning in 1970, the men's and women's programs merged. In 1973 women's intercollegiate athletics was established, with Marie Hartwig as the first administrator. With the settling of the Physical Education faculty in the newly built Central Campus Recreation Building (CCRB) in 1977, and the appointment of Dee Edington as department chair, physical education continued to promote research in exercise and sports science. With Edington's appointment came $60,000 to equip a center for physical fitness and sports research.
In 1984, following a university review of several academic units, Physical Education was separated from the School of Education and became an independent degree-granting academic unit. With this dissolution, physical education continued to broaden beyond teacher certification to developing curricula in such areas as sports management and communication and movement science. In 1990, the Regents approved the name change to the Division of Kinesiology. Dee Edington remained as its director. While the traditional field of physical education continues to stress teaching certification and coaching, the movement science track prepares students for careers in such fields as athletic training, physical therapy, biomedical research and corporate wellness programs, while sports management and communications develops students' skills in facility management, sport marketing, sports journalism, and recreation program administration.
In November 2008 the Regents approved the renaming of the Division as the School of Kinesiology. Noreen Clark was named the interim Dean. Gregory Cartee was appointed to a term as interim Dean, May 1, 2009-Aprl 30, 2010. Ronald Zernicke, director of the Bone and Joint Injury Prevention & Rehabilitation Center, was named Dean of the School beginning January 1 2010.
For further information researchers are advised to consult the publication: Kinesiology: A Michigan Tradition, 1894-1994. A copy of this publication is located in the UM. School of Kinesiology publications record group
Spanning the years 1966-2010, the records of the School of Kinesiology (3.5 linear ft.) document the evolution of the division from a department within a school to a distinct degree-granting body. With material from all three stages of the Division's history, namely the Department of Physical Education (1921-1977), the Division of Physical Education (1984-1990), and the Division of Kinesiology (1990-1999), the records demonstrate a small unit's struggle within a large university and its efforts to garner support both from the university and Ann Arbor community. The record group is comprised of six series: Audio Series, Committee Records, Correspondence, Program Development, Topical Files and Website series. These series stress both the evolution of the division and its intrinsic relationship with the Athletic Department, providing students with practical experience in all of the distinct curriculum areas. Although a majority of the records highlighting the development of Kinesiology are held in the Program Development series, this theme and others reoccur throughout the record group.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. School of Kinesiology.; University of Michigan--Sports.; Margaret Bell Pool (University of Michigan); Hartwig, Marie Dorothy, 1906-; Lindeman, Joyce.; Edington, D. W., 1937-; Athletics--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Movement education--Study and teaching.; Kinesiology.; Physical education and training--Michigan.
- Audio Series
  The Audio Series, which is undated, consists of two cassette tapes. These tapes record two lectures given by former Kinesiology faculty. Included is Marie Hartwig's lecture on Camp Structure.
  - Hartwig, Marie, Camp Structure Lecture (Box 1)
  - Reagan, Health and Safety Standards (Box 1)
- Committee Records
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title, the majority of the Committee Records (1.75 linear ft.) are then chronologically ordered. These records primarily contain meeting minutes, but also include agendas, correspondence and reports debated during the meetings. This series dates from 1976 to 1999.
  - Classroom Committee 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Directors' Meeting 1999 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee
    - 1985 (Box 1)
    - 1987-1990 (Box 1)
    - 1988-1990 (Box 1)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    - 1991-1992 (two folders) (Box 1)
    - 1992-1995 (Box 1)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Meeting
    - 1977-1988 (Box 1)
    - 1984, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1987-1990 (Box 1)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    - 1991 (Box 1)
    - 1992 (Box 1)
    - 1993 (Box 1)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 1)
    - 1997-1998 (Box 1)
    - 1998-1999 (Box 1)
  - Graduate Committee
    - 1989-1991 (Box 1)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - May Retreat
    - 1993 (Box 1)
    - 1994 (Box 1)
    - 1995 (Box 1)
  - Movement Science
    - Agendas and Materials 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - May 1992 (Box 1)
    - May 1993 (Box 1)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 1)
    - 1998-1999 (Box 1)
  - Physical Education
    - 1976 (Box 2)
    - 1991-1995 (Box 2)
  - Search Committee 1985 (Box 2)
  - Sports Management and Communication
    - 1986-1989 (Box 2)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 2)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 2)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - 1995-1996 (Box 2)
    - 1998 (Box 2)
    - Materials 1989-1992, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - May, 1990 (Box 2)
    - May, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Meetings with Dee Edington 1981-1996 (Box 2)
  - Teacher's Education
    - 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - 1991-1995 (Box 2)
  - Unit Heads
    - 1987-1988, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1988-1990 (Box 2)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - circa 1990 (Box 2)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 2)
- Correspondence
  Comprised of memoranda and letters, the Correspondence series (.25 linear ft.) dates from 1989 to1998. The series mainly consists of internal correspondence between the faculty and the Director, Dee Edington. The small remainder of the series demonstrates the relationship between the Athletic Department and the Division.
  - Edington, Dee 1991-1995 (Box 3)
  - Goss, Tom Memos 1998 (Box 3)
  - Lindeman, Joyce 1991-1992 (Box 3)
  - Lindeman, Joyce memos 1991-1992 (Box 3)
  - Teacher's Education memos 1989 (Box 3)
- Program Development
  Focusing specifically on the rise of the Department of Physical Education to its status as the Division of Kinesiology, the series Program Development (.75 linear ft.) demonstrates the deliberate planning and procedures followed in its effort at establishing itself both within the university and within the larger field of kinesiology. Accreditation files, curriculum proposals, and departmental reviews all document this concerted endeavor. The series dates from 1977 to 1999.
  - Association of the American Alliance for Health, PE, Recreation, and Dance (AAHPERD) 1990-1992 (Box 3)
  - Athletic Training
    - 1991-1992 (Box 3)
    - Accreditation 1996-1997 (Box 3)
    - Specialists 1991-1995 (Box 3)
    - Specialists 1996-1999 (Box 3)
  - Career Development Course 1994 (Box 3)
  - Concerns regarding Movement Science, no date (Box 3)
  - Curriculum Ideas from Students for Sports Management and Communication 1991 (Box 3)
  - Elective Course Proposals 1992 (Box 3)
  - Faculty goals 1990-1991 (Box 3)
  - Ideas for Kinesiology Study Tables 1993 (Box 3)
  - Kinesiology Program Survey 1994 (Box 3)
  - Kinesiology Program Survey 1993 (Box 3)
  - Kinesiology Survey Results 1993 (Box 3)
  - K Quality
    - Advising 1994 (Box 3)
    - Internships 1993 (Box 3)
    - Kinesiology Day 1994 (Box 3)
    - Professional Day 1993 (Box 3)
  - Movement Science, Other Programs 1992 (Box 3)
  - Movement Science, Survey Results 1993 (Box 3)
  - National Council for Athletic Training Education (NCATE) Report 1982 (Box 3)
  - NASPE Standards, Accreditation 1991 (Box 3)
  - Official Approvals of Teacher's Education 1986 (Box 3)
  - Paired Faculty Development 1994 (Box 3)
  - PE Core Class Proposal 1992 (Box 3)
  - PE Department Review 1983 (Box 3)
  - PE Transition, Department of 1984-1985 (Box 3)
  - Phase I, Evaluation Final 1977 (Box 3)
  - Planning Documents 1991 (Box 3)
  - Program Planning 1991 (Box 3)
  - Positions Open 1989 (Box 3)
  - Profile Composite 1994 (Box 3)
  - Review, School of Education Materials 1982 (Box 3)
  - Sports Management and Communication Curriculum Focus Group 1996 (Box 3)
  - Sports Management and Communication Curriculum Ideas 1990-1991 (Box 3)
  - Sports Management and Communication Lab Equipment Request 1990 (Box 3)
  - Sports Management and Communication Lab Research Ideas, no date (Box 3)
  - Sports Management and Communication Lab Renovation Projects 1989 (Box 3)
  - Sports Management and Communication Revisions 1989 (Box 3)
  - Sports Management and Communication Staff Goals 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - State of the Division 1984-1992 (Box 3)
  - Teacher Education Revisions, Ann Arbor Teachers' Input 1984-1985 (Box 3)
  - Teacher Education Revisions, Other Programs and Materials 1983-1984 (Box 3)
  - Teaching Improvement Ideas 1991 (Box 3)
  - Vision for Sports Management and Communication 1988 (Box 3)
- Topical Files
  Spanning the years 1966-1996, the Topical Files (.75 linear ft.) are arranged alphabetically. This series contains correspondence, reports, financial statements, meeting notes, and proposals. The subject matter covered includes alumni relations, demographic data, curriculum plans, funding ideas, relations with the Athletic Department, financial information, as well as other matters pertaining to both the undergraduate and graduate programs.
  - Administrative Affairs 1994-1995 (Box 4)
  - Alumni Questionnaire 1990 (Box 4)
  - Aquatic Courses Outlines, circa 1987 (Box 4)
  - Associate Deans for Small Units 1993 (Box 4)
  - Basic Curriculum, Movement Science 1992 (Box 4)
  - Bell Pool, Addition 1985-1986 (Box 4)
  - Bell Pool, Plan 1986 (Box 4)
  - Bell Pool, Teaching Assistant Orientation, circa 1977 (Box 4)
  - Budget 1987 (Box 4)
  - Budget, Sports Management and Communication 1986-1990, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Budget, Sports Management and Communication, Staff Letters 1984 (Box 4)
  - Certificate Program 1996 (Box 4)
  - Computer Ethics 1994 (Box 4)
  - Core Content Movement Science, circa 1992 (Box 4)
  - Course Guidelines First Draft 1987-1988 (Box 4)
  - Curriculum Planning Sports Management and Communication 1990-1991, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Demographic Data Sports Management and Communication in the United States 1993 (Box 4)
  - Directed Teaching Term Reports 1983-1984 (Box 4)
  - Diversity Audit 1990-1993 (Box 4)
  - Edington, Dee, Director 1996 (Box 4)
  - Edington, Dee, Meeting 1991 (Box 4)
  - Enrollment
    - Graduate Figures 1991-1992 (Box 4)
    - Materials
      - 1993-1994 (Box 4)
      - 1994 (Box 4)
    - Meeting
      - 1992 (Box 4)
      - 1994 (Box 4)
  - Evaluation of Teacher Supervision Model 1977 (Box 4)
  - Graduate Funding Ideas 1992 (Box 4)
  - Health Minor 1995 (Box 4)
  - Individually Arranged Courses Draft 1991 (Box 4)
  - Master's Program Article 1992 (Box 4)
  - Movement Science Lab Description 1992 (Box 4)
  - Ocker, Phyllis Retirement Party 1990 (Box 4)
  - PE Alumni Survey 1986-1991 (Box 4)
  - PE Workshop
    - 1994 (Box 4)
    - 1995 (Box 4)
    - 1996 (Box 4)
  - PhD Curriculum Ideas 1992 (Box 4)
  - PhD Survey, Draft 1994 (Box 4)
  - Pre Med for Movement Science Students 1992 (Box 4)
  - Pre Physical Therapy for Movement Science Students 1992 (Box 4)
  - Specialty Tracks, circa 1992 (Box 4)
  - Sports Management and Communication Faculty Activities 1989-1990 (Box 4)
  - Sports Management and Communication 203, no date (Box 4)
  - Student Teacher Manuals, circa 1966 (Box 4)
  - Student Teacher Seminar Payroll 1971-1978 (Box 4)
  - Teacher Corps 1987-1988 (Box 4)
  - Teacher Corps 1992 (Box 4)
  - Teacher Education
    - History 1980 (Box 4)
    - Revisions Final 1986 (Box 4)
    - Revisions and Letters 1986 (Box 4)
  - Undergraduate PE Program 1977-1978 (Box 4)
  - Walter, Timothy 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - Weikart, Phyllis1989-1991 (Box 4)
- Archived School of Kinesiology Website
  The Archived Website series documents the academic programs, accomplishments, resources, events, and people at the School of Kinesiology. Content includes important news and announcements, publications (such as newsletters and course catalogs), and information about admissions, curriculum, degree requirements, faculty, and the overall mission of the School. The website series is arranged chronologically, with captures from 2002 stored on CD. Starting in 2010, this archived website will be captured on a regular, ongoing basis as part of the University of Michigan Web Archives, hosted at http://webarchives.cdlib.org/a/universityofmichigan/.
  - Website capture May 15, 2002, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 2)
  - Website capture, May 22. 2002, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 2)
  - Archived School of Kinesiology home page 2010-[ongoing]
  - Archived websites related to the School of Kinesiology 2010-[ongoing]